Finding Aid for Vincent Castagnacci papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Vincent Castagnacci papers 1957-2010
Castagnacci, Vincent
69.5 GB online
3.5 linear feet
2011012 Aa 2
Professor of Fine Arts at the University of Michigan and widely exhibited painter with studios in Pinckney, Michigan and Gloucester, Massachusetts. Collection includes digital still images, video files, and promotional materials related to Castagnacci's classroom instruction, his artwork, and his personal influences.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Vincent Castagnacci (donor no. 10007 ) in 2008 and 2010.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Vincent Castagnacci papers include restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Box 4
Personnel Records -- Box 4
Vincent Castagnacci was born in Providence, Rhode Island and is a painter with studios in Pinckney, Michigan and Gloucester, Massachusetts. From 1959 to 1962 he studied drawing, painting, printmaking at the Boston Museum School and drawing and sculpture with George Demetrios in Boston and Gloucester, Massachusetts. The Museum School degree program with Tufts University awarded him a BS Ed in 1963. He received a BFA from Yale University in 1964 and continued on at Yale to receive his MFA in 1966. He also pursued occasional studies with Professor Alfredo Barilli in Rome.
While a student at Yale, Castagnacci served as an instructor in basic design at Southern Connecticut State College. From 1966 to 1973, he was an associate professor at Old Dominion University. He joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1973.
Castagnacci's abstract work - in painting, printmaking and drawing - has been centered in the principle of variational development. Through his art, he articulates a personal geometry and communicates a strong sense of tectonic values. His five-year collaboration with percussionist and composer Michael Gould has most recently produced Into the Quarry, an installation celebrating the convergence of art and music in space and time. In addition, he has lectured and published widely in this country, in Rome at L'Istituto Nazionale per la Grafica, and at the Gebaudelehre, Technische Universität in Vienna.
Castagnacci has received numerous grants and fellowships from Michigan and other funding sources. In 1980 he was awarded a citation and grant from the American Academy in Rome where he was visiting artist for nine months. In 1999 he was named Arthur F. Thurnau Distinguished Professor of Fine Arts, one of the highest honors awarded to U of M teaching faculty. He also was a Mellon Scholar at Kalamazoo College.
Castagnacci has exhibited in numerous solo and group exhibitions both here and abroad. In 1996 Hope College mounted a retrospective exhibit "CASTAGNACCI: Works 1968-1995" which was supplemented by an extensive catalogue.
Text taken from: University of Michigan School of Art & Design, "Vincent Castagnacci" (2010). Retrieved on February 2, 2011 from http://art-design.umich.edu/people/detail/vince_castagnacci
The collection is comprised of three series: Teaching and Other Speaking Engagements, Artwork and Exhibitions, and Interviews and Background Materials.
The Vincent Castagnacci collection documents Castagnacci's dual careers as an Professor of Fine Arts and a widely exhibited painter. Teaching materials (lecture notes, handouts, and readings) provide access to his four decades as an educator and are complemented by video footage of his classroom instruction. Digital reproductions of artwork and video of Castagnacci in his studio suggest the range and extent of his creative pursuits. Additional video footage of interviews and conversations with colleagues along with depictions of the natural environs of Gloucester, Massachusetts further contextualize Castagnacci's approach to education and art.
Subjects:
Art--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Artists--Michigan.; Castagnacci, Vincent.; Castagnacci, Vincent--Exhibitions.; Painting--Massachusetts--Gloucester.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Art & Design.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Castagnacci, Vincent.; Art education--Michigan.; Artists--Michigan.; Painting--Massachusetts--Gloucester.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Art & Design.
Contributors:
Gould, Michael.
Genre Terms:
Digital images.; Interviews.; Photographs.; Videotapes.; Websites.
- Teaching and Other Speaking Engagements
  The Teaching and Other Speaking Engagements series documents Castagnacci's career as an instructor at Old Dominion University (from 1967 to 1972) and at the University of Michigan's School of Art & Design (from 1973 until his retirement in 2008). The series consists of lecture notes, readings, and course handouts that span four decades of Castagnacci's career as an educator and which are complemented by video footage of his classroom instruction at the University of Michigan's School of Art & Design in 2004 and fall 2007 (his final semester of teaching). Additional departmental assignments (including work on the Basic Studio committee) and his appointment as an Arthur F. Thurnau Distinguished Professor are documented as well. The series also includes video from the 1995 Mondrian Symposium held at U of M's Chrysler Auditorium that document panelists (including Castagnacci) delivering lectures, a performance of a Mondrian-inspired dance piece, and a reconstruction of Mondrian's final studio in New York.
  - Basic studio committee
    - Background materials and supporting documents, 1957-1974 (Box 1)
    - Draft report, circa 1975 (Box 1)
    - Interview and meeting transcripts, circa 1970s (Box 1)
    - Meeting materials, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Pilot program, 1974-1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Report, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Graduate students, 1989-1991 (Box 4)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2065 ]
    - Colleagues, 1990-1994 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2024 ]
  - Course descriptions, circa 1990s (Box 1)
  - Course evaluations
    - Color, 2004-2006, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Drawing, undated, 2004-2006, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Course materials: lecture notes, class work, and handouts
    - Anatomy and advanced drawing, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Art and architecture convergence course, 1991-1993, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Basic design
      - Undated (Box 1)
      - 1976 (Box 1)
      - 1978 (Box 1)
      - 1980 (Box 1)
    - Color
      - 1977-1979, 5 folders (Box 1)
      - 1988-1992, 8 folders (Box 1)
      - 1992 (Box 2)
      - 1999-2006, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Drawing
      - 1968-1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1990-2006, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Painting
      - 1967-1970, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1984-1986 (Box 2)
      - 1998-2003 (Box 2)
    - Various
      - 1980-1986, 11 folders (Box 2)
      - 1990-2000 (Box 2)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 2)
  - Graduate student reviews, circa 1990 (Box 4)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2074 ]
  - Classroom Instruction
    - Color and Drawing Classes, 2004 and 2007, .MP4 files
    - Digital videocassettes, 20 videotapes Mini-DV? (Box 2)
      Some additional footage of Castagnacci's Color and Drawing classroom instruction May be located among tapes.
  - Piet Mondrian Symposium, 1995, .MP4 files
    - "Mondrian: The Education of Vision," 1995
      (Panel discussion on Piet Mondrian featuring Dean of the School of Art Allen Samuels, painter Vincent Castagnacci, sculptor Michael Kapetan, designer Jack Williamson, architectural historian Anatole Senkevitch, and Jason Holtzman, trustee of the Mondrian-Holtzman Trust)
    - "Mondrian Boogie," 1995
      (Dance work choreographed by Associate Professor of Dance Jessica Fogel with music by Assistant Professor Stephen Rush)
    - "Mondrian at Slusser," 1995
      (Recreation of Mondrian's last studio in New York at the University of Michigan's Slusser Gallery)
  - Music information for studio teaching, undated (Box 3)
  - Pedagogy ("Thoughts on Teaching"), 2000-2005 (Box 3)
  - Recognition
    - Faculty profile (in Visualize newsletter), 1994 (Box 3)
    - Thurnau Distinguished Professor appointment (announcements), 1999-2000 (Box 3)
  - Student work: Basic painting self-assessments, 2001-2004 (Box 4)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2079 ]
  - Undergraduate curriculum committee, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Writings
    - School of Art curriculum description, undated (Box 3)
      (Remarks prepared for visiting parents)
    - School of Art & Design assessment, undated (Box 3)
      (Written to Dean Allen Samuels)
- Artwork and Exhibitions
  The Artwork and Exhibitions series provides an overview of Castagnacci's art, his work in the studio, and promotional materials for several exhibitions. Catalogs from exhibits in 1989 and 1996 explore the variations and underlying ideas of his work. Video footage of his collaboration with percussionist and University of Michigan faculty member Michael Gould captures the early conversations and experiments that led to their 2006 exhibition. Digital reproductions represent various phases of his drawings and paintings, including his series "Bend in the Road," "Four Corners," "Isola di Giglio," "Rome Variations," and "Stereotomia," among others. Still images also document the display of his "Rome Monotypes" and a 2004 show at Kalamazoo College's Light Fine Arts Gallery. Three videos from 2004 depict Castagnacci at work on a printing press and giving a tour of artwork in his studio. Promotional materials include a PowerPoint for his 2010 show "Notes from a Quarry" at the River Gallery in Dexter, Michigan as well as several flyers from other exhibitions.
  - Catalogs
    - Elements of Persistence, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Works: 1968-1995, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Collaboration with Michael Gould (U of M music faculty), 2003-2005, .MP4 files
    (Includes conversations and an experiment in which Gould records the sound of Castagnacci at work)
  - Digital reproductions, circa 1960-2000, .ZIP files
    - Bend in the Road series, circa 1994
    - Four Corners series, undated '
    - Gloucester (Mass.) drawings, undated
    - Isola di Giglio series, circa 1998
    - Light Fine Art Gallery exhibition (Kalamazoo College), 2004
    - Rome Monotypes, 1980
    - Rome Variations, 1987-1988
    - Stereotomia series, circa 1999
    - Other works, circa 1960-2000
  - Promotional Materials
    - Notes from a Quarry Exhibit, 2010, .PPS and .PDF files
      River Gallery in Dexter, Michigan
    - Rome Monotypes exhibit, 1981 (Box 3)
      (Slusser Gallery, University of Michigan)
    - University of Michigan Faculty exhibit, undated (Box 3)
      (Mott Community College Fine Arts Gallery)
  - Studio work, 2004, .MP4 files
    (Includes tour of Castagnacci's studio and footage of Castagnacci working on a printing press)
  - Archived Website
    - 2008
    - 2010-2014
- Interviews and Background Materials
  The Interviews and Background Materials series contains materials that contextualize Castagnacci's work as a professor and artist. Still images document the quarries and seascapes of Gloucester, Massachusetts as well as Italian street scenes and architectural features that are reflected in his work. Videos provide insight into Castagnacci's personal influences and experiences and include interviews of him by videographer Peter Knox and artist Kevin Brady; a narrated visit to Halibut Point Quarry; and conversations with two of his mentors, the artists Bernard Chaet and Ralph Coburn. The series also includes Personal Bedrock, a biographical video by Peter Knox that explores the evolution of Castagnacci's artistic philosophy and his creative work.
  - Photographs of Gloucester (Mass.) and Italy, undated, .ZIP files
  - Moving Images
    - Interviews conducted by Peter Knox and Kevin Brady; conversations with Bernard Chaet and Ralph Coburn; and footage from Gloucester, Massachusetts, circa 2004, .MP4 files
      Includes biographical piece, "Personal Bedrock."
    - Digital videocassettes, 15 videotapes Mini-DV? (Box 3)
      May include some footage of Castagnacci's classroom instruction)